<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://glyph-cat.github.io/cotton-box/blog</id>
    <title>Cotton Box Blog</title>
    <updated>2024-03-31T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://glyph-cat.github.io/cotton-box/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Cotton Box Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://glyph-cat.github.io/cotton-box/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reincarnation of an old package]]></title>
        <id>https://glyph-cat.github.io/cotton-box/blog/reincarnation-of-an-old-package</id>
        <link href="https://glyph-cat.github.io/cotton-box/blog/reincarnation-of-an-old-package"/>
        <updated>2024-03-31T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In 2020, react-relink was released. It was heavily inspired by recoil and had a similar API design.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 2020, <a href="https://github.com/glyph-cat/react-relink" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><code>react-relink</code></a> was released. It was heavily inspired by <a href="https://github.com/facebookexperimental/Recoil" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><code>recoil</code></a> and had a similar API design.</p>
<br>
<p><code>react-relink</code> was created with the goals of:</p>
<ol>
<li>not needing to wrap components in <a href="https://react.dev/reference/react/createContext#provider" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Providers</a> while still allowing states to be shared across different React components trees, and</li>
<li>make it easy to transition from <code>recoil</code> by introducing similar concepts and APIs.</li>
</ol>
<br>
<p>As time goes on, the concepts of <code>recoil</code> were slowly disregarded, new features were added, and <code>react-relink</code> began to evolve into a state management library of it's own.</p>
<br>
<p>At that point, there were three main problems...</p>
<ul>
<li>The codebase became bloated and difficult to maintain</li>
<li>It became so slow, that in some scenarios, it results in very noticeable lagging</li>
<li>There was no easy way to use <code>react-relink</code> as a state management tool outside of React because the dependencies are tied together.</li>
</ul>
<br>
<p>Eventually, the better solution was to create <del>a new package</del> two new packages —
a core package and another one for its React bindings. This allows non-React projects to use this new state management library without needing to install <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/react" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer"><code>react</code></a> as a dependency, and the core package is called <code>cotton-box</code>.</p>
<p><code>cotton-box</code> exposes three different types of State Managers that are built on top of one another for different needs:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>SimpleStateManager</code> —&nbsp;the most lightweight state manager</li>
<li><code>StateManager</code> - generic state manager with lifecycle hooks for persisting data</li>
<li><code>AsyncStateManager</code> - similar to <code>StateManager</code> but supports async set-state functions</li>
</ul>
<p>More information on the differences between these State Managers are available <a href="https://glyph-cat.github.io/cotton-box/docs/learn/tutorial/which-state-manager-should-i-use">here</a>.</p>
<p>If you're migrating from <code>react-relink</code>, it is highly recommended to check out the <a href="https://glyph-cat.github.io/cotton-box/docs/learn/react/migration-from-react-relink">migration guide</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>GlyphCat</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/glyph-cat</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="react" term="react"/>
        <category label="react-relink" term="react-relink"/>
    </entry>
</feed>